{
  "reference_number": "9134",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "I recommend that NZ takes a phased approach. Adopt Net Zero Carbon by eg 2030 and Net Zero Emissions by 2050. NZ has the\n\n opportunity to be a world leader in emissions reduction technology. Given that methane makes up nearly half of our emissions and\n has a much higher warming potential than CO2 leaving it out of the scheme just doesn’t make sense"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "NZ should be able to participate in international carbon trading, including allowing other countries to buy our (hopefully) excess\n carbon credits. Being isolated from the wider world limits our opportunities"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Unsure. There is a need for a long term approach to provide certainty for business. I would be concerned about government changes\n\n (elections) every 3 years potentially leading to meddling with budgets and targets. Could all 5 year budgets/targets be set at the\n beginning (ie setting objectives right through to 2050), but with allowance for changes by the Climate Commission?"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "Refer previous comment to question 5"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Refer previous comment to question 5"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Please add matauranga Maori and cultural issues as a consideration"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There should be both goals and actions to achieve them (but keep it brief to prevent drowning the process in paperwork)"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Use of a combination of economic, regulatory and voluntary measures. Prioritise incentives and innovation over restrictive rules. Work\n\nwith business, industry, science and the rural sector, as well as community and iwi"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. They go together like jaffas and snifters"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "No. You don’t need new systems. Climate change adaptation should be incorporated into the existing planning framework at regional\nand/or local council level, with policy set at national level"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "No. Adaptation should be managed under the planning (RMA) framework. But if it is set up it should be voluntary"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "New Zealand used to be a world leader in environmental management. We have the opportunity to do this again with an ambitious\n\nclimate change policy. NZ has the enviable position of already having a large portion of our electricity from renewable sources, making\nthe transition to Net Zero an easier reality than many other countries. Yes, we have high emissions from agriculture, but this provides\n\na unique opportunity to develop emission reduction technology and expertise that we can export around the world. Moreover, there\nis clear evidence that industrial scale agriculture has adversely impacted our natural environment and tarnished our clean, green\nimage. Net Zero will see marginal land returned to forest, a much more sustainable alternative. Being an island nation at the mercy of\n\nthe weather and oceans Net Zero is also in our own self interest. Thank you for the opportunity to have my say. If any part of my\nsubmission is published please only use my initial and surname (not my full name)."
    }
  ]
}
